<p>FITS is a very well-established format for storage of
astronomical table or image data
(see <a href="https://fits.gsfc.nasa.gov/">https://fits.gsfc.nasa.gov/</a>).
This writer stores tables in BINTABLE extensions of a FITS file.
</p>

<p>There are a number of variations in exactly how the table data is
written to FITS.
These can be configured with <code>name=value</code> options in brackets
as described below, but for most purposes this isn't required;
you can just choose <code>fits</code> or one of the standard
aliases for commonly-used combinations like <code>colfits</code>
or <code>fits-basic</code>.
</p>

<p>In all cases the output from this handler is legal FITS,
but some non-standard conventions are used:
<dl>
<dt>fits-plus</dt>
<dd><p>In "fits-plus" format, the primary HDU contains an array of bytes
    which stores the full table metadata as the text of a VOTable document,
    along with headers that indicate this has been done.
    Most FITS table readers will ignore this altogether and treat the
    file just as if it contained only the table.
    When it is re-read by this or compatible applications however,
    they can read out the metadata and make it available for use.
    In this way you can store your data in the efficient and widely portable
    FITS format without losing the additional metadata such as table parameters,
    column UCDs, lengthy column descriptions etc that may be attached
    to the table.
    This variant, which is the default, can be explicitly selected with the
    <code>primary=votable</code> option or <code>fits-plus</code> alias
    (if you don't want it,
    use <code>primary=basic</code> or <code>fits-basic</code>).
    </p></dd>
<dt>colfits</dt>
<dd><p>In Column-Oriented FITS output, the HDU containing the table data,
    instead of containing a multi-row table, contains a single-row table
    in which each cell is an (nrow-element) array containing the data
    for an entire column.
    The point of this is to keep all the data for a single row
    localised on the disk rather than scattered through the whole file.
    This can be more efficient for certain applications,
    especially when the table is larger than physical memory,
    and has many columns of which only a few are needed for a particular task,
    for instance plotting two columns against each other.
    The overhead for writing this format is somewhat higher than for
    normal (row-oriented) FITS however, and other FITS table applications
    may not be able to work with it,  so in most cases normal FITS
    is a better choice.
    This variant can be selected with the
    <code>col=true</code> option or the <code>colfits-plus/colfits-basic</code>
    aliases.
    If you write to a file with the "<code>.colfits</code>" extension
    it is used by default.
    </p></dd>
<dt>wide</dt>
<dd><p>A private convention is used where required
    to support encoding of tables with
    more than 999 columns (not possible in standard FITS);
    this was discussed on the FITSBITS mailing list in July 2017
    in the thread
    <a href="https://listmgr.nrao.edu/pipermail/fitsbits/2017-July/002967.html"
       >BINTABLE convention for >999 columns</a>.
    If software unaware of this convention (e.g. CFITSIO) is used
    to read such tables, it will only see the first 998 columns written
    as intended, plus a column 999 containing an undescribed byte buffer
    where the rest of the column data is stored.
    </p></dd>
</dl>
</p>

<p>For convenience, and compatibility with earlier versions,
these standard aliases are provided:
<dl>
<dt>fits-plus</dt>
<dd><p>Alias for <code>fits</code> or <code>fits(primary=votable)</code>.
    </p></dd>
<dt>fits-basic</dt>
<dd><p>Alias for <code>fits(primary=basic)</code>.
    </p></dd>
<dt>fits-var</dt>
<dd><p>Alias for <code>fits(primary=basic,var=true)</code>.
    </p></dd>
<dt>colfits-plus</dt>
<dd><p>Alias for <code>fits(col=true)</code>.
    </p></dd>
<dt>colfits-basic</dt>
<dd><p>Alias for <code>fits(col=true,primary=basic)</code>.
    </p></dd>
<dt>fits-healpix</dt>
<dd><p>This is a special case.
    It is used for storing HEALPix pixel data in a way that conforms to the
    <a
    href="https://healpix.sourceforge.io/data/examples/healpix_fits_specs.pdf"
       >HEALPix-FITS</a>
    serialization convention.
    In most ways it behaves the same as <code>fits-basic</code>,
    but it will rearrange and rename columns as required to follow
    the convention, and it will fail if the table does not contain
    the required HEALPix metadata (<code>STIL_HPX_*</code> parameters).
    </p></dd>
</dl>
</p>
