<p>In many cases tables are stored in some sort of unstructured plain
text format, with cells separated by spaces or some other delimiters.
There is a wide variety of such formats depending on what delimiters
are used, how columns are identified, whether blank values are permitted
and so on.  It is impossible to cope with them all, but the ASCII handler
attempts to make a good guess about how to interpret a given ASCII file as
a table, which in many cases is successful.  In particular, if you just
have columns of numbers separated by something that looks like spaces,
you should be just fine.
</p>

<p>Despite the name, by default it reads Unicode characters in the UTF-8
encoding.  It can if necessary be restricted to ASCII characters only
by setting the <code>encoding</code> option.
</p>

<p>Here are the detailed rules for how the ASCII-format tables are
interpreted:
<ul>
<li>Bytes in the file are interpreted as ASCII characters</li>
<li>Each table row is represented by a single line of text</li>
<li>Lines are terminated by one or more contiguous line termination
    characters: line feed (0x0A) or carriage return (0x0D)</li>
<li>Within a line, fields are separated by one or more whitespace
    characters: space (" ") or tab (0x09)</li>
<li>A field is either an unquoted sequence of non-whitespace characters,
    or a sequence of non-newline characters between matching
    single (') or double (") quote characters -
    spaces are therefore allowed in quoted fields</li>
<li>Within a quoted field, whitespace characters are permitted and are
    treated literally</li>
<li>Within a quoted field, any character preceded by a backslash character
    ("\") is treated literally.  This allows quote characters to appear
    within a quoted string.</li>
<li>An empty quoted string (two adjacent quotes)
    or the string "<code>null</code>" (unquoted) represents
    the null value</li>
<li>All data lines must contain the same number of fields (this is the
    number of columns in the table)</li>
<li>The data type of a column is guessed according to the fields that
    appear in the table.  If all the fields in one column can be parsed
    as integers (or null values), then that column will turn into an
    integer-type column.  The types that are tried, in order of
    preference, are:
       <code>Boolean</code>,
       <code>Short</code>
       <code>Integer</code>,
       <code>Long</code>,
       <code>Float</code>,
       <code>Double</code>,
       <code>String</code>
    </li>
<li>Some special values are permitted for floating point columns:
    <code>NaN</code> for not-a-number, which is treated the same as a
    null value for most purposes, and <code>Infinity</code> or <code>inf</code>
    for infinity (with or without a preceding +/- sign).
    These values are matched case-insensitively.</li>
<li>Empty lines are ignored</li>
<li>Anything after a hash character "#" (except one in a quoted string)
    on a line is ignored as far as table data goes;
    any line which starts with a "!" is also ignored.
    However, lines which start with a "#" or "!" at the start of the table
    (before any data lines) will be interpreted as metadata as follows:
    <ul>
    <li>The last "#"/"!"-starting line before the first data line may
        contain
        the column names.  If it has the same number of fields as
        there are columns in the table, each field will be taken to be
        the title of the corresponding column.  Otherwise, it will be
        taken as a normal comment line.</li>
    <li>Any comment lines before the first data line not covered by the
        above will be concatenated to form the "description" parameter
        of the table.</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>

<p>If the list of rules above looks frightening, don't worry,
in many cases it ought
to make sense of a table without you having to read the small print.
Here is an example of a suitable ASCII-format table:
<pre>
    #
    # Here is a list of some animals.
    #
    # RECNO  SPECIES         NAME         LEGS   HEIGHT/m
      1      pig             "Pigling Bland"  4  0.8
      2      cow             Daisy        4      2
      3      goldfish        Dobbin       ""     0.05
      4      ant             ""           6      0.001
      5      ant             ""           6      0.001
      6      ant             ''           6      0.001
      7      "queen ant"     'Ma\'am'     6      2e-3
      8      human           "Mark"       2      1.8
</pre>
In this case it will identify the following columns:
<pre>
    Name       Type
    ----       ----
    RECNO      Short
    SPECIES    String
    NAME       String
    LEGS       Short
    HEIGHT/m   Float
</pre>
It will also use the text "<code>Here is a list of some animals</code>"
as the Description parameter of the table.
Without any of the comment lines, it would still interpret the table,
but the columns would be given the names <code>col1</code>..<code>col5</code>.
</p>
