<p>FITS is a very well-established format for storage of
astronomical table or image data
(see <a href="https://fits.gsfc.nasa.gov/">https://fits.gsfc.nasa.gov/</a>).
This writer stores tables in a FITS file consisting of two HDUs
(Header+Data Units): a Primary HDU as required by the FITS standard,
and a single extension of type BINTABLE containing the table data.
</p>

<p>There are a few variants of this format:
<dl>

<dt>fits-plus</dt>
<dd><p>The primary HDU contains an array of bytes
    which stores the full table metadata as the text of a VOTable document,
    along with headers that mark this has been done.
    Most FITS table readers will ignore this altogether and treat the
    file just as if it contained only the table.
    When it is re-read by this or compatible applications however,
    they can read out the metadata and make it available for use.
    In this way you can store your data in the efficient and widely portable
    FITS format without losing the additional metadata such as table parameters,
    column UCDs, lengthy column descriptions etc that may be attached
    to the table.
    </p></dd>

<dt>fits-basic</dt>
<dd><p>The primary HDU contains only very minimal headers and no data.
    </p></dd>

<dt>fits-var</dt>
<dd><p>Behaves like <code>fits-basic</code>, but columns containing
    variable-length numeric array data are stored using the <code>P</code>
    and <code>Q</code> formats where appropriate, rather than padding
    smaller arrays to the size of the largest.
    This can make for more compact storage of variable-length array-valued
    column data but may also result in tables less suitable for streaming.
    </p></dd>

<dt>fits-healpix</dt>
<dd><p>Used for storing HEALPix pixel data in a way that conforms to the
    <a
    href="https://healpix.sourceforge.io/data/examples/healpix_fits_specs.pdf"
       >HEALPix-FITS</a>
    serialization convention.
    In most ways it behaves the same as <code>fits-basic</code>,
    but it will rearrange and rename columns as required to follow
    the convention, and it will fail if the table does not contain
    the required HEALPix metadata (<code>STIL_HPX_*</code> parameters).
    </p></dd>

</dl>
The default output format is <code>fits-plus</code>;
in general you don't need to worry about this,
it just gives you some hidden benefits over <code>fits-basic</code>.
</p>

<p>A private convention is used where required
to support encoding of tables with
more than 999 columns (not possible in standard FITS);
this was discussed on the FITSBITS mailing list in July 2017
in the thread
<a href="https://listmgr.nrao.edu/pipermail/fitsbits/2017-July/002967.html"
   >BINTABLE convention for >999 columns</a>.
If software unaware of this convention (e.g. CFITSIO) is used
to read such tables, it will only see the first 998 columns written
as intended, plus a column 999 containing an undescribed byte buffer.
</p>
